Having dealt with class diagrams, and in
particular also with the validity of class
diagrams (i.e., the constraints that
exist on class diagrams when
considering the various relationships), we
now come to object diagrams.
So obviously the
specification of individual objects.
An object, we know, is
an expression of a class.
And what you're seeing here is a slide
that you've seen something similar or exactly the same.
So we have a class, and then we discussed
(and this also came up in the exercise) when then
an object is an instantiation of
it (so it instantiates this class).
Reminder:
In particular, all attributes
had to be occupied.
If this was a
subclass of another class,
then the attributes of the
superclass would also appear here.
What does not appear,
however, are the methods.
Because they have no place
in an object (with this
kind of modeling
we are doing here).
That would
be an object.
An object diagram is
then obviously a diagram
in which several such objects occur,
which are possibly related to each other.
Where the relationships that
should/could exist there would
depend on
a class diagram.
So you have to have a valid
class diagram, and then you can talk
about creating an object
diagram to that class diagram.
The idea
here is:
If the class diagram puts in the framework of how
a system can be designed, then an object diagram would
be sort of a snapshot or a snapshot
of the system at a point in time.
In other words, a set of objects with
their relationships to each other as they might be
present in a system at a particular
point in time that satisfies the class diagram.
A class diagram was used to
record what types of actors should exist,
what attributes exist, how
the classes are related.
An object diagram must then
be a concrete manifestation of
this (which, of course, adheres to everything
that was modeled in the class diagram).
The point is that
we then have a
clear mapping of, for example,
the various associations and the properties.
The multiplicities have to
be roughly adhered to.
So we have to fulfill
everything that the class diagram
specifies, also in
a corresponding object diagram.
Thereby the
objects get names.
We have here perhaps a class "Point"
and then several individual points, here "myPoint".
We could also have
"myPoint1" or "myPoint2" here.
So the objects have an identity,
which can be represented by a name.
But an object
could also remain anonymous.
Sometimes the name
part is simply
omitted if it is not important to
the object that it has a name.
But the class must be specified so that
we know which class this object is from.
Then we would simply have something
like this as a specification, and
say: "Object of the class Point"; and in front
of it, however, there would be no concrete name.
So that this object
would have no proper name,
but would simply remain an
anonymous object of the corresponding class.
We will not include the
classes themselves in the object diagram.
We will have separately a class
diagram and then a matching object diagram.
So not the situation where both are
in one diagram with these extra arrows.
We're not going
to do that here.
You can do that, but that's
not going to happen in our tasks.
Then I had just said that
in the objects we assign the attributes
that are predefined
by the classes.
UML does not
necessarily always require this.
UML also allows that we do not assign
all attributes of an object, because perhaps not all
attributes are relevant for the concrete
situation that is to be represented.
Of course, the situation is different if
we require (for example, in the exercise or
exam) that you should
make a complete instantiation.
That is, that
you should occupy
all attributes that are predefined by
the class definition in the object.
If you refrain from this
requirement (i.e., you don't explicitly
require this, as we might do
in the exercise or exam), then you
could certainly represent instantiations of
abstract classes in the object diagram.
Although I had
said last week that
you cannot instantiate objects from
abstract class in a concrete implementation.
For such a representation of the
object diagram it would be in principle
also possible to form an
embodiment of an abstract class.
Of course, under the circumstances that not
all attributes are occupied (which would be necessary
if we would specify objects from
a concrete subclass of the abstract class).
And
very important:
There are no
inheritance arrows between objects.
We will see in a moment how the
other relationships that exist at the class level
(association, aggregation, composition) are
reflected in the object diagram.
The inheritance arrows between classes in
the class diagram, on the other hand,
have no equivalent in the object
diagram, because we specify concrete objects there.
An object then belongs
to a concrete class.
This can be a class from
a class hierarchy with several inheritances.
But this one
object we are mapping
belongs to *one* class and
does *not* inherit from another object.
Rather, it belongs to a class
that may inherit from other classes.
The inheritance arrows that exist between
classes do not exist between objects.
Because of the
concepts of inheritance, superclasses,
subclasses, objects could in principle
also have a superclass specified.
If we remember the "Points"
and the "ColouredPoints", then we
could have
a concrete "ColouredPoint".
So a concrete object
of the class "ColouredPoint".
This is also an
object of the class "Point".
Therefore, in this specification, a superclass should also
be specified, if we don't want to have
this more precise again in the exercise
or the exam, or explicitly exclude it.
I had already spoken about the
fact that we do not find
the inheritance arrows in the object
diagram, but the other relationships do.
How do we find
them in the object diagram?
By means of the notion of
"link", which is simply also a
link, but now
any relationship between objects.
If we have an association on the class
level, or an aggregation, or a composition, then
this can be found on the level
of the objects of the corresponding classes
by means of a connecting
line, a link, a connection.
These are then quite concrete expressions of
such a relationship of specific objects of
the classes involved in the
relationship existing on class level.
There are no multiplicities
attached to the links.
The multiplicities in the
class diagram tell us
how many objects of this or that
type can be involved in such a relationship.
In the object diagram we
always have very concrete objects.
So a link represents exactly
one relationship between two concrete objects.
And although this may be an
expression of an association with multiplicities,
these multiplicities will not
be attached to this link.
Of course, they still
have to be observed.
So you don't see on a
concrete link which multiplicities are prevalent there.
Because that's
a class-level concept.
But if we look at
the entire object diagram, then
of course it has to satisfy
the multiplicities from the class diagram.
So if the class
diagram specifies "there are
objects of class A related to a
maximum of two objects of class B";
then we just can't have one object of
class A and three objects of class B in
the object diagram, so that this A
object is related to all three B objects.
Finally, the multiplicity conditions of
the class diagram must be respected.
That is, the numbers of
objects that are related must
be within
their respective bounds.
But there is not a
number attached to each link somehow.
Because these numbers
span all links.
This is a
requirement for all links
that exist between objects of one
class and objects of another class.
We will see in the example
how this is to be understood.
Let's take an example
that we had before and
extend it a little bit
or build two examples together.
Once we had the example
with parking lot and cars.
Then at some point we
also had a situation with cars
and owners, and on the whiteboard slides
I had also once related cars and wheels.
Always these two
pairs of classes.
Let's put that into a
larger, extended class diagram, where we
have the parking lot with an
aggregation to car with corresponding multiplicities here.
And the car has an aggregation
to wheel, again with certain multiplicities.
Different from the example that
I had looked at on
the whiteboard, I really have
the 1 here at the composition.
In the other example I had
said, a wheel could be also
in the camp, then
just in no car.
Here it
is more specific.
So there's just this
one composition here, and
there's also the ownership, so there's
an association of person to car.
So now we have
three different kinds of relationships.
Now we don't have
inheritance in this example.
Of course, we
can create object diagrams
from class diagrams
that contain inheritance.
Then we have to
remember, first of all,
that the subclasses inherit all their relationships
from the superclasses in addition to their attributes.
So that's one
possible class diagram.
Now we can take a look at what
an object diagram might look like for this.
We need to decide how
many cars we want to have.
Let's take at least two, because it
would be boring with only one car.
Let's take two
cars that should exist.
Then we
already know:
Each car can be in
zero or one parking space.
Let's say there is a parking lot
that happens to have these two cars.
We
also know:
Each car has exactly four wheels, and
no wheel can belong to two cars.
That is, if we have two cars, we
will probably have exactly eight wheels as other objects.
And then each car must
also have an owner, exactly one.
However, one owner can own several
cars, for example up to five.
So what might a concrete object
diagram to this class diagram look like?
For example,
as follows:
This is the
situation we had.
For example, here as an object
is a concrete parking lot, namely
the one in the L-area
of the campus in Duisburg.
That would be "Name-of-object is
object of the class parking lot".
What I did here
now in the example times,
is that I omitted
everywhere the attribute boxes.
Actually, for all
attributes, which are
mentioned here in the second box,
there would be assignments here as well.
We will also have
that sometimes in the exercises,
that we stylize the objects and partly also
the classes in such a way that we actually
only have the box with the name and
not also the two boxes for attributes and methods.
So this
one parking space.
Then I had talked about two cars, for
example a green Skoda and a black Ford.
These are each cars as
different instantiations of the class car,
and they're both contained
in this one parking lot.
So these two links here
are expressions of this one relationship.
Then there's an owner in each
case, which are instantiations of this class.
These are these two person
objects here, Peter and Gabi.
It could also
be just one owner.
There could also be another link
from Gabi to the green Skoda.
But then this object, or this
relationship here, would have to disappear.
Because Gabi and Peter can't both
be owners of the green Skoda,
because each car has
only exactly one owner.
Then there is
this relation here.
To each car belong exactly four wheels,
therefore we have here four wheels each.
I just left
them as anonymous objects.
These are four different wheels, but
they are not distinguished by names.
Nevertheless, there are in any
case four and here again four,
thus altogether
eight different objects.
They are just not named like "front
left wheel of the green Skoda" or so.
Here we
see again:
For each incarnation of the
composition there is a link.
The green Skoda has links to exactly
four wheels, and so does the black Ford.
And they each have exactly one
link to the car containing them.
So this is enough
for these multiplicities here.
But they are not
attached to the links themselves,
because that makes no
sense for a single link.
What is important is that, for example,
these four links together satisfy these constraints
here, which result from the
composition here with the corresponding multiplicities.
Now if we were to start
deleting objects or deleting links or
adding more objects, we
could always ask ourselves:
Does it still
satisfy this class diagram?
If I specify
a fifth wheel here,
and also link it to the green
Skoda, then I would have a violation.
Because then I would have assigned five
wheels to the green Skoda, which is forbidden.
If I added a wheel without connecting
it to any car, I would have
violated the class
diagram as well.
Because to this wheel there would not be
then the exactly one car, which it contains.
Which, however, must exist
according to this specification here.
Of course, this is not
the only suitable object diagram.
But many changes we could make
locally now would violate the class diagram.
However, there are other object diagrams
that also fit this class diagram.
One task in the exercises or even the
exam could be to decide for a class
diagram and an object diagram whether this
object diagram fits to this class diagram.
Or to set up an object diagram
of a certain size for a class diagram.
Two
more comments:
We could certainly, even though I
didn't do it in the example
just now, also note the aggregation
and composition symbols in the object diagram.
Since these four links are manifestations of
this composition, one could also draw this filled
diamond at each of these four places
here, and of course also here below.
But you
don't have to.
Likewise, you can
omit the association name.
Here I did it for the
sake of clarity, so that you
know what these
two associations are.
It is not obligatory
to write them there.
This is done mainly
for the sake of clarity.
Which was perhaps not necessary here, because
exactly four wheels belong to it anyway.
There was no
need to emphasize that
they belong to
the composition symbol.
Or to
add a name.
Here there
is the name.
It could have been written in these
four places, but it doesn't have to be.
The same applies to
reading direction and navigation direction.
This is what
it says here:
Association name, navigation direction and
reading direction can also be omitted.
We will also have object diagrams
where just the links are drawn in
without any further
annotations on them.
I had already
pronounced this "attention" message:
We must remember, of course, when
specifying an object diagram or checking
the fit to a class
diagram, that relationships (i.e., associations,
aggregations, compositions) are
inherited between classes.
If a class has relationships of this
type to another class, then they are also
present in the subclass, so must
be considered for objects of the subclass.
Example:
Suppose we have a class
Account and two subclasses of it,
and we have a
relationship of customers to accounts.
In particular, each account must have exactly
one owner, a customer who owns it.
Then savings accounts and checking accounts
must also have exactly one owner
each, even though there is no
explicit relationship of these to customers.
They inherit that because
they are subclasses of account.
That is, an object
diagram might look like this:
Suppose we have exactly two accounts,
a savings account and a checking account.
Then they must
each have an owner.
They could also
have the same owner.
A customer may have several
accounts, because nothing is restricted here.
But each current account or savings
account must have exactly one owner.
There could also be a
second object, another customer, who
would own the savings account
and Klaus only the checking account.
That would
also be allowed.
What would not be allowed, however,
would be that there is simply another
savings account or another current
account, which have no owner.
Because then this requirement
would not be fulfilled.
Of course, it would also not be allowed
that there is another customer and the savings
account would be owned by Klaus
as well as by this other customer.
Because that would also
contradict this 1 here.
Further discussion on the fit
of object diagrams to class
diagrams, with at least one
more example, by extra video.